<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_DqScPH6">An Efficient and Robust Data Compression Algorithm in Wireless Sensor Networks</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName coords="2,196.56,108.68,148.66,9.63"><roleName>Senior Member, IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Yao</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
							<email>yliang@cs.iupui.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer and Information Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Indiana University Purdue University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>46202</postCode>
									<settlement>Indianapolis</settlement>
									<region>IN</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName coords="2,374.03,108.68,40.37,9.63"><forename type="first">Yimei</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer and Information Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Indiana University Purdue University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>46202</postCode>
									<settlement>Indianapolis</settlement>
									<region>IN</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_3444zVG">An Efficient and Robust Data Compression Algorithm in Wireless Sensor Networks</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">EBAC8B4996AD6F0897A450B9BD4769A0</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1109/LCOMM.2014.011214.132319</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2" ident="GROBID" when="2023-05-07T13:56+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term xml:id="_bEQCVTv">Wireless sensor networks</term>
					<term xml:id="_9eKmF8G">data compression</term>
					<term xml:id="_MVCP45P">energy efficiency</term>
					<term xml:id="_APkCfh7">robustness</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_Ycuud33"><p xml:id="_tgcY9q2">Data compression is a useful technique in the deployments of resource-constrained wireless sensor networks (WSNs) for energy conservation. In this letter, we present a new lossless data compression algorithm in WSNs. Compared to existing WSN data compression algorithms, our proposed algorithm is not only efficient but also highly robust for diverse WSN data sets with very different characteristics. Using various real-world WSN data sets, we show that the proposed algorithm significantly outperforms existing popular lossless compression algorithms for WSNs such as LEC and S-LZW. The robustness of our algorithm has been demonstrated, and the insight is provided. The energy consumption of our devised algorithm is also analyzed.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="4" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
		<surface n="5" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_Nbyvaf2">I. INTRODUCTION</head><p xml:id="_6GRQDn4">W IRELESS sensor networks (WSNs) are being increas- ingly deployed for enabling continuous monitoring and sensing of physical variables of our world. Energy efficiency is of paramount importance in the design and deployment of wireless sensor networks, as WSN nodes are typically battery-powered, and in many real physical environments the replacement of batteries for nodes is either difficult or virtually impossible. In general, radio transmissions and receptions are most power consuming compared to the energy consumption of node microcontroller and memory in WSNs. Because sensing data usually exhibit strong temporal correlations, data compression has been considered as a useful approach to reducing power consumptions of WSN nodes. Recent advances in lossless temporal compression include compression algorithms such as Sensor LZW (S-LZW) <ref type="bibr" coords="2,200.79,513.02,11.70,8.76" target="#b0">[1]</ref> and Lossless Entropy Compression (LEC) <ref type="bibr" coords="2,132.13,524.90,10.68,8.76" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" coords="2,148.79,524.90,10.68,8.76" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, and compression framework such as Two-Modal Transmission (TMT) <ref type="bibr" coords="2,197.56,536.90,10.68,8.76" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" coords="2,214.82,536.90,10.68,8.76" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, in which various entropy coding algorithms can be employed.</p><p xml:id="_hWsJHM9">an encoder are employed. For a new data item x i in a series, xi is generated by a given predictor, and residue r i = x i − xi is calculated. This residue r i is coded, and then transmitted to the receiving node. In LEC, the simple and popular differential predictor is adopted, that is, xi = x i−1 ; the contribution of LEC is its encoder which is a modified version of the Exponential-Golomb code (Exp-Golomb) of order 0 <ref type="bibr" coords="2,528.24,226.10,10.68,8.76" target="#b8">[9]</ref>.</p><p xml:id="_f2E3emu">While LEC demonstrated significantly better compression performance in comparison with S-LZW in <ref type="bibr" coords="2,497.28,249.98,10.69,8.76" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, one critical challenge of LEC and other practical data compression algorithms is the robustness, which indicates whether or not a data compression algorithm can be widely and effectively applied for diverse real-world sensor data in various WSN applications, for different sensor data can exhibit very different temporal characteristics. This motivated our work. The differential predictor in LEC is generic without any training/leaning when applied to any sensed data streams, making LEC is simple to use and scalable for large-size WSNs. However, such a generic and non-adaptive predictor cannot effectively exploit temporal correlations for diverse WSN data streams for various WSN applications, because different sensed data streams exhibit different temporal correlation patterns. As a result, while LEC may show good compression performance for some sensed data streams in a WSN, it may also produce poor performance for other data streams in other WSNs. In other words, LEC suffers from its lack of robustness.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_8nCATxZ">B. Contributions</head><p xml:id="_6ePH3TE">In this letter, we present a novel, efficient and robust lossless data compression algorithm which is able to significantly improve temporal lossless compression performance in WSNs for data collections. Our devised algorithm extends the LEC to address its weakness of the lack of robustness, and hence is able to achieve highly robust compression performance for various sensor data streams. At the same time, our algorithm is sufficiently simple to enable its energy-efficient implementation and execution on resource-constrained WSN nodes. Our algorithm, referred to as Sequential Lossless Entropy Compression (S-LEC), is proposed in Sec. II. We provide careful and rigorous evaluation of our algorithm in comparison with recent S-LZW and LEC compression algorithms using diverse real-world WSN data sets in Sec. III. Finally we present energy analysis of our devised algorithm versus LEC in Sec. IV to validate our algorithm.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_dyBJWty">II. ALGORITHM</head><p xml:id="_x4Ns8me">In LEC, residues in residue series {r i } (i = 1, 2, 3, . . . , M, where M is the size of data block), being coded by the entropy encoder, are considered having no correlation among them, 1089-7798/14$31.00 c 2014 IEEE and thus are encoded independently. Our insight is that since the simple differential predictor is generic for any sensed data streams, it cannot completely capture and remove the temporal correlations among an arbitrary sensor data sequence. Based on the implicit assumption of residue independence, LEC would perform reasonably if the correlation characteristic of a sensor data stream is roughly captured by the differential predictor, but would perform poorly otherwise. To address this issue, we introduce a novel idea of sequential coding and extend LEC. In the following, before we present our S-LEC algorithm, we first briefly overview LEC.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_AGEv4gW">A. Overview of LEC</head><p xml:id="_HdbrgDh">As a modified version of the Exponential-Golomb code, LEC organizes the alphabet of integer residues obtained from differential predictor into groups which have exponentially increased sizes <ref type="bibr" coords="3,112.42,531.50,10.66,8.76" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" coords="3,129.66,531.50,10.66,8.76" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. Generally, an LEC codeword consists of two parts: the entropy code specifying the group and the binary code representing the index in the group. Assume that any sensor reading x i is represented in K bits, K + 1 groups are to be formed. When residue r i is not zero, it is represented as h i |a i , where h i = h(n i ) encodes the group number n i (n i = log 2 |r i | + 1) and a i represents the following computed index within the group as binary code:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0" coords="3,100.80,632.74,146.88,25.05">index = r i , r i &gt; 0 2 ni − |r i | − 1, r i &lt; 0 .</formula><p xml:id="_KVhuCgY">When residue r i equals to zero, then the corresponding group number n i = 0 and also no index (i.e., no a i code) is needed. An LEC coding table, for K = 24 for example, is shown in Table <ref type="table" coords="3,74.28,701.30,2.93,8.76" target="#tab_0">I</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_FdXj9bH">B. S-LEC Algorithm</head><p xml:id="_vbYzs5T">To address the robustness issue of the original LEC approach, we devise Sequential LEC (S-LEC) algorithm to ex-   <ref type="table" coords="3,346.55,456.14,6.15,8.76" target="#tab_0">II</ref>. We note that s 1 , for the first residue r 1 of a sensed data block, will be always omitted, and hence h 1 has to be present.</p><formula xml:id="formula_1" coords="3,319.92,102.04,233.44,43.35">01 h i = h(n i−1 − 1), n i−1 ≥ 1 h(2), n i−1 = 0 ; neighboring group 10 h i = h(n i−1 + 1), n i−1 &lt; K h(K − 2), n i−1 = K ; neighboring</formula><p xml:id="_a5AzkNG">In the case of s i = 11, while group code h i cannot be omitted completely, it can be reduced in its size in some context situations without any ambiguity. To investigate this possibility, let all groups of LEC alphabet be further grouped into three clusters as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2" coords="3,311.40,539.26,250.89,22.65">C 1 = {n i |i = 0, 1, 2, 3}, C 2 = {n i |i = 4,</formula><p xml:id="_9KXMwN3">5}, and C 3 = {n i |i = 6, . . . , K}, where K is the number of bits of a sensor reading, that is, the precision of A/D converter (ADC). Then we give h i reduction rule based on</p><formula xml:id="formula_3" coords="3,311.40,587.02,250.62,22.65">r i−1 ∈ C j (j = 1, 2, 3) in Table III when s i = 11 and n i &gt; n i−1 .</formula><p xml:id="_SyBcy6q">To illustrate, for example, let us consider a series of residues r 1 = 9, r 2 = 128, r 3 = −130, r 4 = 16, and r 5 = −32, which will be encoded by S-LEC as 101|1001, 11|1110|10000000, 00|01111101, 11|110|10000, 10|011111. In contrast, the same residue series would be encoded by LEC as 101|1001, 111110|10000000, 111110|01111101, 110|10000, 1110|011111.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_R8N7gyE">III. PERFORMANCE EVALUATION</head><p xml:id="_WQFnnXt">To evaluate the proposed S-LEC algorithm, we compare its lossless compression performance with LEC algorithm and S-LZW algorithm, as LEC and S-LZW represent two different popular algorithms in lossless compression. We use real-world diverse WSN datasets from SensorScope <ref type="bibr" coords="4,225.50,70.46,16.74,8.76" target="#b9">[10]</ref> and volcanic monitoring <ref type="bibr" coords="4,98.98,82.46,15.43,8.76" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" coords="4,123.82,82.46,16.74,8.76" target="#b11">[12]</ref> in our evaluation. The compression performance is usually evaluated by compression ratio defined as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4" coords="4,69.96,120.96,208.68,22.79">CR = (1 − z z ) × 100% = (1 − z K × N × 100%),</formula><p xml:id="_qmTsXf3">where z and z denote the original raw data size and the compressed data size in bits, respectively; N is the number of data samples, and K is the fixed bits per raw sample specified by the precision of the A/D converter used.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_PB3Ds7M">A. Data Sets</head><p xml:id="_jb7v7aW">First, real-world environmental monitoring WSN datasets from SensorScope are used <ref type="bibr" coords="4,165.62,241.82,15.41,8.76" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. To compare with LEC and S-LZW, the same temperature and relative humidity measurements from the following two SensorScope deployments are tested: LUCE and Le Gnpi. The size of the sensor data sets used ranges from 21523 samples to 64913 samples. Both temperature and relative humidity sensors are connected to an ADC. The outputs of ADC for the raw temperature (raw t) and raw relative humidity (raw h) are represented with resolutions of 14 and 12 bits, respectively. These raw outputs raw t and raw h are then converted into physical measures t and h expressed, respectively, in Celsius degrees and percentage (%) as described in <ref type="bibr" coords="4,179.85,373.34,15.40,8.76" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. The data sets published on SensorScope corresponding to the two deployments are in the format of physical measures t and h. Therefore, one needs to convert such physical measures back to their corresponding raw measures to evaluate compression algorithms, which can be realized by using the inverted versions of the conversion functions in <ref type="bibr" coords="4,100.81,445.10,15.43,8.76" target="#b13">[14]</ref>.</p><p xml:id="_Fu65wge">Then, real-world volcanic monitoring WSN seismic data sets are used <ref type="bibr" coords="4,106.59,469.10,15.41,8.76">[15]</ref>, collected via a 19-day WSN deployment at Reventador, an active volcano in Ecuador <ref type="bibr" coords="4,237.70,481.10,15.41,8.76" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" coords="4,260.83,481.10,15.41,8.76" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. The resolution of sampled seismic signals is 24 bits, and sample rate is 100Hz. The size of the seismic data sets used ranges from 7885 samples to 8268 samples. Unlike the relatively smooth SensorScope temperature and relative humidity data, the seismic data of volcanic eruptions are highly dynamic, presenting challenges to data compression approaches. The volcanic data 2005-08-11 03.36.40 from <ref type="bibr" coords="4,220.93,564.74,16.74,8.76">[15]</ref> is used in our experiment, whose range is projected from the normalized (-1,1) to their original (0, 2 24 -1) to obtain raw ADC readings.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_BpxkeaX">B. Compression Results</head><p xml:id="_ShPYHd8">To make a direct comparison with the results of LEC and S-LZW reported in <ref type="bibr" coords="4,128.44,644.42,10.68,8.76" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, we follow the same assumptions made in <ref type="bibr" coords="4,60.00,656.42,11.70,8.76" target="#b2">[3]</ref> for SensorScope WSN data sets: (1) a raw temperature (raw t) sample and a raw relative humidity (raw h) sample will take 16 bits when transmitted uncompressed; and (2) the size of each data block M for compression is 264 samples. Table IV lists the lossless compression performance of S-LEC, LEC and S-LZW, using SensorScope temperature and relative humidity data sets.</p><p xml:id="_Xvmk9y6">For volcanic data sets, the data block size used for compression is 176 samples. Five sensor nodes' sampled data are  employed and the lossless compression performance of S-LEC and LEC is listed in Table <ref type="table" coords="4,423.50,287.42,4.84,8.76" target="#tab_4">V</ref>.</p><p xml:id="_HPfzSxR">It can be seen from Table <ref type="table" coords="4,431.80,300.50,10.55,8.76" target="#tab_4">IV</ref> that the compression performance of the proposed S-LEC achieves better compression performance than both LEC and S-LZW on all different SensorScope WSN data sets.</p><p xml:id="_JnAK3Fw">Next, we focus on comparisons between S-LEC and LEC, as both LEC and S-LEC have significantly better compression ratios than S-LZW shown in Table <ref type="table" coords="4,470.64,373.34,8.70,8.76" target="#tab_4">IV</ref>. We observe that, from Table V, S-LEC and LEC have dramatically different performance results on volcano WSN data sets, although their performance difference for SensorScope data sets are mild. As we can see in Table <ref type="table" coords="4,391.18,421.22,4.84,8.76" target="#tab_4">V</ref>, S-LEC improves the compression ratios by a factor of more than two in comparison with LEC for the first four sensor nodes' data sets. In particular, for node 251, while S-LEC can still achieve more than 25% compression ratio, LEC completely fails.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_HcAygZj">C. Discussions</head><p xml:id="_JvkXw6X">These two groups of comparison results on two different real-world WSN dada sets reveal some interesting fact that LEC can perform extremely different depending on the characteristics of WSN data sets. While LEC could perform well on Sensorscope WSN temperature and relative humidity measurements that are quite smooth, it performs poorly on WSN volcanic data that are very dynamic. The insight is that LECs coding table (Table <ref type="table" coords="4,439.51,608.66,3.34,8.76" target="#tab_0">I</ref>) is optimized when residues generated from sampled data concentrate on zero and follow a Laplace-like distribution. Since the smooth WSN data at SensorScope largely satisfy this assumption, LEC can lead to good compression performance. However, volcanic data are very dynamic and their residues do not follow the distribution assumed by the LEC entropy encoder, which eventually fails LEC approach. In contrast, the proposed S-LEC can perform well for both smooth WSN data and dynamic WSN data, due to its capability to exploit temporal information remained in residue series, which demonstrates a high degree of robustness of S-LEC for diverse WSN data sets in broad real-world applications and deployments. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_QTJQ9B3">IV. ENERGY CONSUMPTION ANALYSIS</head><p xml:id="_HkSeTC7">A simplified energy consumption model on source sensor nodes for the proposed S-LEC can be obtained by counting the number of basic operations (e.g., shifts, additions) conducted in S-LEC algorithm. For example, it needs n shifts in the encoder to obtain the code if the residue is in the n th group of the coding table. Thus, based on simulation, we can obtain the actual operation numbers needed for each data set in the following energy consumption analysis. Considering the widely used CC2420 radio transceiver and ARM7TDMI microprocessor of motes, we use the parameters of energy consumption model given in <ref type="bibr" coords="5,168.98,294.02,10.69,8.76" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. Consider one hop transmission in the following analysis. Therefore, transmitting k bytes per hop requires</p><formula xml:id="formula_5" coords="5,89.28,335.50,169.80,10.65">E radio (k) = kI T X V T T X + kI RX V T RX .</formula><p xml:id="_kYstAdp">Denote N add , N sht , and N cmp the number of add, shift, and comparison operation, respectively. The total computation energy consumption would be</p><formula xml:id="formula_6" coords="5,82.44,396.10,183.60,10.65">E comp = N add add + N sht sht + N cmp cmp ,</formula><p xml:id="_3J6Cwjt">where add , sht and cmp are the energy consumption of addition, shift and comparison instruction respectively, given in <ref type="bibr" coords="5,60.24,439.22,10.68,8.76" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. Then, the total energy consumption is computed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_7" coords="5,129.36,456.70,89.64,10.65">E = E radio + E comp .</formula><p xml:id="_hMnTJEg">Based on the above energy consumption model, we computed the total energy consumption of lossless compression in a one-hop WSN for both S-LEC and LEC, as shown in Table <ref type="table" coords="5,48.96,511.82,10.52,8.76" target="#tab_4">VI</ref> (including both E radio and E comp ). The energy analysis was conducted on SensorScope data sets for which LEC can perform well. We can observe that S-LEC is overall more energy efficient than LEC, even in a one-hop WSN. This indicates that the communication energy savings achieved by S-LEC exceeds its computation energy cost of slightly more processing compared to LEC. Clearly, the energy savings of S-LEC over LEC on the dynamic volcano data sets will be dramatically higher. Furthermore, as the number of hops in a WSN increases, significantly more energy savings of S-LEC over LEC will be achieved.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head xml:id="_JHPAmVq">V. CONCLUSION</head><p xml:id="_XBtaQBg">We extend and modify the previous LEC and devise Sequential LEC (S-LEC) algorithm for efficient and robust data compression in WSNs. We evaluate the S-LEC using the realworld WSN diverse data sets including smooth temperature and relative humidity data and dynamic volcanic data that exhibit dramatic different characteristics. Our results show that S-LEC significantly outperforms the recent popular data compression algorithms S-LZW and LEC. In particular, while the performance of LEC is very sensitive to the characteristics of WSN data series, S-LEC shows a high degree of robustness regardless of the dramatic characteristics exhibited in diverse WSN data series. We also conduct energy consumption analysis for S-LEC versus LEC on SensorScope data sets, indicating the better overall energy efficiency of S-LEC than LEC even for those smooth sensor data sets in a one-hop WSN. For dynamic WSN data series such as volcano data in multi-hop WSNs, the energy efficiency of S-LEC compared to LEC will be significantly greater. Hence, the robustness and efficacy of S-LEC make it very suitable for data collection in various real-world WSN deployments.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" coords="3,67.20,53.18,213.75,259.51"><head>TABLE I</head><label>I</label><figDesc xml:id="_FrEwsuf"></figDesc><table coords="3,67.20,62.18,213.75,250.51"><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">LEC CODING TABLE FOR K=24</cell></row><row><cell>n i</cell><cell>h(n i )</cell><cell>r i</cell></row><row><cell>0</cell><cell>00</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>010</cell><cell>±1</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell>011</cell><cell>±2, ±3</cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>±4, • • • ± 7</cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell>101</cell><cell>±8, • • • ± 15</cell></row><row><cell>5</cell><cell>110</cell><cell>±16, • • • ± 31</cell></row><row><cell>6</cell><cell>1110</cell><cell>±32, • • • ± 63</cell></row><row><cell>7</cell><cell>11110</cell><cell>±64, • • • ± 127</cell></row><row><cell>8</cell><cell>111110</cell><cell>±128, • • • ± 255</cell></row><row><cell>9</cell><cell>1111110</cell><cell>±256, • • • ± 511</cell></row><row><cell>10</cell><cell>11111110</cell><cell>±512, • • • ± 1023</cell></row><row><cell>11</cell><cell>111111110</cell><cell>±1024, • • • ± 2047</cell></row><row><cell>12</cell><cell>1111111110</cell><cell>±2048, • • • ± 4095</cell></row><row><cell>13</cell><cell>11111111110</cell><cell>±4096, • • • ± 8191</cell></row><row><cell>14</cell><cell>111111111110</cell><cell>±8192, • • • ± 16383</cell></row><row><cell>15</cell><cell>1111111111110</cell><cell>±16384, • • • ± 32767</cell></row><row><cell>16</cell><cell>11111111111110</cell><cell>±32768, • • • ± 65535</cell></row><row><cell>17</cell><cell>111111111111110</cell><cell>±65536, • • • ± 131071</cell></row><row><cell>18</cell><cell>1111111111111110</cell><cell>±131072, • • • ± 262143</cell></row><row><cell>19</cell><cell>11111111111111110</cell><cell>±262144, • • • ± 524287</cell></row><row><cell>20</cell><cell>111111111111111110</cell><cell>±524288, • • • ± 1048575</cell></row><row><cell>21</cell><cell>1111111111111111110</cell><cell>±1048576, • • • ± 2097151</cell></row><row><cell>22</cell><cell>11111111111111111110</cell><cell>±2097152, • • • ± 4194303</cell></row><row><cell>23</cell><cell>111111111111111111110</cell><cell>±4194304, • • • ± 8388607</cell></row><row><cell>24</cell><cell>1111111111111111111110</cell><cell>±8388608, • • • ± 16777215</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4" coords="4,323.88,156.62,225.89,88.85"><head>TABLE V</head><label>V</label><figDesc xml:id="_veRSwGn"></figDesc><table coords="4,323.88,165.62,225.89,79.85"><row><cell cols="3">COMPRESSION PERFORMANCE COMPARISONS ON VOLCANO DATA</cell></row><row><cell>Data Set</cell><cell cols="2">Compression Ratio CR(%) S-LEC LEC</cell></row><row><cell>Node 200</cell><cell>30.99</cell><cell>12.65</cell></row><row><cell>Node 201</cell><cell>28.31</cell><cell>9.76</cell></row><row><cell>Node 202</cell><cell>31.27</cell><cell>13.91</cell></row><row><cell>Node 205</cell><cell>26.76</cell><cell>4.40</cell></row><row><cell>Node 251</cell><cell>25.08</cell><cell>-0.39</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="funding">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="_pQEgb8R"><p xml:id="_PTzscNv">This work is supported in part by the U.S. National Science Foundation under grant CNS-1252066.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct coords="5,329.61,316.46,232.39,7.01;5,329.64,325.46,232.23,7.01;5,329.64,334.34,232.27,7.01;5,329.64,343.34,29.71,7.01" xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_E8MN5Yc">Data compression algorithms for energy-constrained devices in delay tolerant networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName coords=""><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Sadler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName coords=""><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Martonosi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_hrPJECp">Proc. 2006 International Conference on Embedded Networked Sensor Systems</title>
				<meeting>2006 International Conference on Embedded Networked Sensor Systems</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="265" to="278" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="5,329.64,352.70,232.13,7.01;5,329.64,361.70,232.29,7.01;5,329.64,370.70,50.60,7.01" xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_U7khdEy">A simple algorithm for data compression in wireless sensor networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName coords=""><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Marcelloni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName coords=""><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Vecchio</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_S6bT4g6">IEEE Commun. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="411" to="413" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="5,329.60,380.06,232.37,7.01;5,329.64,389.06,232.27,7.01;5,329.64,398.06,63.32,7.01" xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_QVe5QDx">An efficient lossless compression algorithm for tiny nodes of monitoring wireless sensor networks</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_99j8Utk">The Computer J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="969" to="987" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="5,329.64,407.42,232.09,7.01;5,329.64,416.42,232.21,7.01;5,329.64,425.30,185.12,7.01" xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_RUhPYBC">Minimizing energy consumptions in wireless sensor networks via two-modal transmission</title>
		<author>
			<persName coords=""><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName coords=""><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Peng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_dj2NJQC">ACM SIGCOMM Computer Commun. Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12" to="18" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="5,329.64,434.66,231.87,7.01;5,329.64,443.66,232.25,7.01;5,329.64,452.73,232.18,6.84;5,329.64,461.66,56.71,7.01" xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_eBY5Pw5">Towards energy optimization in environmental wireless sensor networks for lossless and reliable data gathering</title>
		<author>
			<persName coords=""><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName coords=""><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_8SCXeTh">Proc. 2007 IEEE Internatonal Conference on Mobile Adhoc and Sensor Systems</title>
				<meeting>2007 IEEE Internatonal Conference on Mobile Adhoc and Sensor Systems</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="6" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="5,329.61,471.02,232.18,7.01;5,329.64,480.02,137.12,7.01" xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_7ch3wGY">A technique for high-performance data compression</title>
		<author>
			<persName coords=""><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Welch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_qSyhk9H">Computer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8" to="19" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="5,329.60,489.38,232.32,7.01;5,329.64,498.38,42.56,7.01" xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_eMBvZDg">Predictive coding-i</title>
		<author>
			<persName coords=""><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Elias</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_XFKU7SF">IRE Trans. Inf. Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16" to="24" />
			<date type="published" when="1955">1955</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="5,329.60,507.74,232.32,7.01;5,329.64,516.74,42.56,7.01" xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_DBWPDvU">Predictive coding-ii</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_7FGewkw">IRE Trans. Inf. Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="24" to="33" />
			<date type="published" when="1955">1955</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="5,329.60,526.10,232.31,7.01;5,329.64,534.98,157.28,7.01" xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_eKwvJ6n">A compression method for clustered bit-vectors</title>
		<author>
			<persName coords=""><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Teuhola</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_ShH6wkw">Inf. Process. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="308" to="311" />
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="5,329.60,544.46,232.24,7.01;5,329.64,553.34,232.04,7.01;5,329.64,562.34,232.21,7.01;5,329.64,571.34,101.95,7.01" xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_RZhSfC8">Sensorscope: out-of-the-box environmental monitoring</title>
		<author>
			<persName coords=""><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Barrenetxea</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName coords=""><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Ingelrest</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName coords=""><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Schaefer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName coords=""><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Vetterli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName coords=""><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Couach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName coords=""><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Parlange</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_kXFWgVh">Proc. 2008 International Conference on Information Processing in Sensor Networks</title>
				<meeting>2008 International Conference on Information essing in Sensor Networks</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="332" to="343" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="5,329.60,580.70,232.30,7.01;5,329.64,589.70,232.04,7.01;5,329.64,598.70,225.56,7.01" xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_VSsBM4p">Deploying a wireless sensor network on an active volcano</title>
		<author>
			<persName coords=""><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Werner-Allen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName coords=""><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Lorincz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName coords=""><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ruiz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName coords=""><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Marcillo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName coords=""><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName coords=""><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lees</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName coords=""><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Welsh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j" xml:id="_YdMfAPy">IEEE Internet Computing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="18" to="25" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="5,329.62,608.06,232.31,7.01;5,329.64,617.06,232.27,7.01;5,329.64,625.94,232.27,7.01;5,329.64,634.94,29.71,7.01" xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main" xml:id="_qBjdDmw">Fidelity and yield in a volcano monitoring sensor network</title>
		<author>
			<persName coords=""><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Werner-Allen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName coords=""><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Lorincz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName coords=""><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName coords=""><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lees</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName coords=""><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Welsh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" xml:id="_BfzsQgE">Proc. 2006 Symposium on Operating Systems Design and Implementation</title>
				<meeting>2006 Symposium on Operating Systems Design and Implementation</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="381" to="396" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="5,329.59,644.30,231.75,7.01;5,329.64,653.30,62.78,7.01" xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_TSHTE3t">Sensorscope homepage</title>
		<ptr target="http://lcav.epfl.ch/op/edit/sensorscope-en" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013-10">2013. Oct</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="5,329.59,662.66,229.94,7.01;5,311.40,672.02,249.88,7.01;5,329.64,681.02,25.71,7.01" xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main" xml:id="_aGqaj4T">Sensirion homepage</title>
		<ptr target="http://fiji.eecs.harvard.edu/Volcano" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013-10">2013. Oct. 2013. Oct</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
